<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Posts on Dhole&#39;s blog </title>
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/index.xml</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 03:33:57 CET</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emulating a GameBoy Cartridge with an STM32F4. Part 1</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/gameboy_cartridge_emu_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 03:33:57 CET</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/gameboy_cartridge_emu_1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following project consists on emulating the functionality of a GameBoy
cartridge with the development board STM32F4. The system is fully functional
and is able to emulate real cartridges (as well as homebrew games) of the type
ROM Only and MBC1 (Memory Block Controller 1). In this post I will explain
how I managed to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current flashcart systems commonly use a design consisting on a FPGA or CPLD
controlling the logic of the emulated cartridge (memory banking, RAM access,
etc.), a media storage (flash chip or SD card) and an SDRAM chip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way this flashcarts work is that upon booting the console, they present a
small program that list the roms available in the media storage. The user selects
a game and the FPGA copies it from the media storage to the SDRAM to allow
fast access. Once the rom has been copied, the FPGA acts as a gateway mapping
the contents of the SDRAM to the original cartridge mappings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the GameBoy cartridges use small ROM chips for which one can find
compatible FLASH chips in the market, it is a viable alternative to the FPGA
to take an original cartridge with a MBC5 and swap the original ROM chip with
a compatible FLASH memory. A cartridge with MBC5 is often selected because with
it, games with ROM Only and games using MBC1 can also be run (There is
compatibility). With this setup, the user is able to reprogram the FLASH many
times with different games and play them on the GameBoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This procedure is detailed here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.digital-circuitry.com/DOC/NINTENDO/GAMEBOY/DIY%20Nintendo%20GAMEBOY%20Classic%20Flash%20Cartridge.pdf&#34;&gt;DIY Nintendo GAMEBOY Classic Flash Cartridge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FPGA system seems to allow much more freedom but it also involves more work:
the MBC5 (or the supported Memory Block Controllers) must be implemented in
hardware, an interface to access the media storage must be designed, the circuit
must be designed too with all the componentes (FPGA/CPLD, FLASH/SD Reader, SDRAM,
&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative to this one can think of would be to use a microcontroller
instead, interfacing the cartridge pins through the GPIO. This design can have
many complications since the timings to perform a read / write operation are
quite tight. The microcontroller should be fast enough to perform this operations
at the bus speed. When adding the functionality of the Memory Block controller
the timings could be hard to achieve. Alex from Inside Gadgets attemted to
achieve this using an Arduino. The low frequency of the Arduino made this project
infeasible, although Alex was able to achive the emulation of the Nintendo logo,
due to the fact that when the gameboy boots, the first read of the Nintendo logo
from the cartridge is timming predictable and not too fast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insidegadgets.com/2011/04/23/emulating-the-nintendo-logo-on-the-gameboy/&#34;&gt;Emulating the Nintendo Logo on the Gameboy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My aim was to try to implement a cartridge emulator using a faster microcontroller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;The hardware&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this project I choosed the STM32F4 Discovery. This development board features an ARM Cortex-M4 which can run at 168MHz, with 1 MB Flash, 192 KB RAM and more than
70 GPIO. The GPIO are accessed through a peripherials bus that can run at 100MHz.
I also considered other boards such as the Teensy 3.1 but I ended up choosing
the STM32F4 because it had more Flash and RAM and because it was unexpensive (14€)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side, the GameBoy CPU runs at 4MHz. The comercial cartridges have
up to 512 KB of ROM and 128 KB of RAM, although the MBC5 is capable of handling
more ROM. Many cartridges have a MBC (Memory Block Controler) (such as the MBC5
or the MBC1). This controller allows the catridge to handle ROMs that don&amp;rsquo;t fit
into the GameBoy memory area reserved for the cartridge ROM by means of bank
selection. This selections are performed by writting into specific areas of the
memory map reserved for the ROM (So that the MBC can handle them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to notice that the GameBoy works at 5V whereas the STM32F4 works
at 3.3V. Connecting 5V signals to the GPIOs of a 3.3 microcontroller can be
dangerous and damage the GPIO peripherials. Luckily the STM32F4-Discovery has
5V tolerance for most of the pins. To see which ones you can check the
documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A list of characteristics of the comercial cartridges can be found here:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.devrs.com/gb/files/gbmbcsiz.txt&#34;&gt;GB Cart List&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these characteristics it seems this project can be doable. If we consider
that the gameboy will perform at most a read / write per cycle (We will later
see that this is not the case), we are left with 42 cycles of our board to handle
the operation. Taking into account that the GPIO bus is clocked at 100MHz, there
will be some delay which will leave us fewer cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Analyzing the bus&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to get an idea of how the bus used by the GameBoy to access the
cartridge works I decided to perform some captures using a Logic Analyzer. Since
I don&amp;rsquo;t have any hardware logic analyzer, I will use a an awesome project
which consists of an implementation of a logic analyzer for the STM32F4, which
uses the SUMP protocol to interface with the PC (SUMP is a standard protocol for
hardware logic analyzers to interface with the client side). The logicdiscovery
allows to sample up to 20MHz on 16 channels, with up to 24k samples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://code.google.com/p/logicdiscovery/&#34;&gt;logicdiscovery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The client used is the Logic Sniffer, an open source Java client compatible with
the SUMP protocol:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lxtreme.nl/ols/&#34;&gt;Logic Sniffer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to analyze the bus while the GameBoy was performing reads and writes to
the cartridge, I soldered an FDD ribbon to the main board of the GameBoy,
intercepting the cartridge pins as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/gb_ribbon_1.jpg&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/gb_ribbon_1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Back of the GameBoy PCB with the cartridge pins soldered to a FDD ribbon.&#34; /&gt;
    
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Back of the GameBoy PCB with the cartridge pins soldered to a FDD ribbon.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since only 16 channels are available for the logicdiscovery I decided to monitor
the CLK, RD, WR, CS, DATA {0-4} and ADDR {0-8}. (That is, the lower 4 bits of
the data and the lower 8 bits of the address). With this we should be able to
get information about the timings of the different operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GameBoy cartridge pinout is well known, so it&amp;rsquo;s easy to figure out what every
pin on the PCB of the GameBoy does from a pinout picture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.insidegadgets.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/IMG_1994.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;GameBoy cartridge pinout. Image from www.insidegadgets.com&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        GameBoy cartridge pinout. Image from www.insidegadgets.com
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon analyzing the bus with the BATMAN game (ROM Only cartridge), the following is obtained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/screen_dump_overview.png&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/screen_dump_overview.png&#34; alt=&#34;Logic capture overview&#34; /&gt;
    
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Logic capture overview
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I noticed is that the CLK is at 1MHz, this is good news for us:
we have more cycles for each operation. One oddity I found with the capture is
that we can see that the WR goes low a few times (WR is active on low). The
BATMAN cartridge doesn&amp;rsquo;t have RAM nor Memory Block Controller, so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make
sense to write into it. Since we only have half of the adressess, we can&amp;rsquo;t say
for certain where the data is being written, but my guess is that we are seeing
writes being done to the internal GameBoy RAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can take a closer look to a read and a write and analyze what&amp;rsquo;s happening and
when. This information will give us an idea on when should we perform the reading
of the adresses for a write/read operation, and when to output the data on a
read operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that we have a 20MHz sampling rate, this means that a sample is being
taken every 50 ns, leading to an error of +/- 25 ns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/screen_dump_read_timings.png&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/screen_dump_read_timings.png&#34; alt=&#34;Read timings&#34; /&gt;
    
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Read timings
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/screen_dump_write_timings.png&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/screen_dump_write_timings.png&#34; alt=&#34;Write timings&#34; /&gt;
    
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Write timings
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that for a read operation, the GameBoy leaves WR and CS unactivate
(high) and the RD active (low). This is the default. The GameBoy sets the
address 150ns after the CLK rise, and that the data is available in the bus
(coming from the cartridge) 200 ns later. We can&amp;rsquo;t say when the GameBoy reads
the data, but a guess would be around the CLK fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the write operation, the RD is set to unactive at the same time the address
and the data is set in the bus (150 ns after CLK rise). 100 ns later the CS is
activated. At the CLK fall, the WR is activated, allowing the cartridge to perform
the write for 300 ns. On the next cycle, we can see that RD and CS are reset to
the default state (low and high, active and unactive respectively). Notice that
the CS (Chip Select) is not strictly needed, although it seems to be used only
when accessing RAM (this is not clear).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing timing analysis are sound with the analysis found in the unnoficial
&lt;a href=&#34;http://marc.rawer.de/Gameboy/Docs/GBCPUman.pdf&#34;&gt;GameBoy CPU Manual&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    
    &lt;a href=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/cpu_manual_timing.png&#34;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/cpu_manual_timing_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;RAM timings, taken from the Game Boy CPU Manual. Click for detailed timings.&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        RAM timings, taken from the Game Boy CPU Manual. Click for detailed timings.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we know that the information seen in the bus is not only the communication
between the GameBoy and the cartridge but all the read/write operations of the
GameBoy to its memory map, we can understand the following capture, which shows
a DMA operation (The GameBoy has a DMA functionality to allow to fast copy contents
from RAM or ROM to the OAM (Object Atribute Memory), used by the screen to draw
sprites):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/screen_dump_DMA.png&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/screen_dump_DMA.png&#34; alt=&#34;DMA in action&#34; /&gt;
    
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        DMA in action
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following post I will write about the implementation of the cartridge
emulator. Stay tunned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/media/gameboy_stm32f4/dhole_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;Custom logo featuring my nickname and a cute Dhole&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Custom logo featuring my nickname and a cute Dhole
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 17:04:11 CET</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/first/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had been planning on creating a blog to write about the stuff I do on my free time for a while.
In this blog I plan to write about the projects I develop as well as talking about interesting things
I lean about technology, hardware, security, embedded systems, programming languages and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought was to use a WordPress hosted at wordpress.com, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want the adds. I searched
on the net for alternatives and found out about the static website generators, which allow you to host
the content in a static web server such as your github personal page. Right now this blog is posted in
my server, but I may move it to github if there is some traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The platform choosen is &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;: a static website engine written in Go. There were
other options such as Jekyll and Oktopress, but I decided to try this one because I love Go and because
it&amp;rsquo;s really fast at generating the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you arround!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>