<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Dhole&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Dhole&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 20:54:53 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Thinkpad Helix 2 with Linux</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/thinkpad_helix2_linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 20:54:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/thinkpad_helix2_linux/</guid>
      <description>Preface Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve bought a second hand Thinkpad Helix 2nd Gen with the intention of using it mainly as a tablet to read PDF documents and comics (although I may use it for Internet browsing and occasional development). I like running free software on my computers and so I decided to use GNU/Linux with this tablet/laptop. Here I will explain all the issues I encountered and how I solved them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pulseaudio for multi-user Linux</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/pulseaudio_multiple_users/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 20:54:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/pulseaudio_multiple_users/</guid>
      <description>My setup For some time I&amp;rsquo;ve been using several unix users for my daily work in my desktop computer. After trying out Qubes OS for some time (an OS that achieves security by compartmentalization: different kinds of activites are performed in a different VM, isolating the data of each activity from each other), I came back to GNU/Linux and realized that there&amp;rsquo;s already a security separation in Unix (albeit not as secure as virtualization as in Qubes): users.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming Game Boy Chinese cartridges with an STM32F4</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_cartridge_rw_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2018 00:33:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_cartridge_rw_1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction For the past few years I have been interested in the Game Boy: I&amp;rsquo;ve written an emulator in C (without sound), I developed a physical cartridge &amp;ldquo;emulator&amp;rdquo; using a microcontroller, and most recently I&amp;rsquo;ve built a project to interface my PC with the Game Link. I&amp;rsquo;ve also played a bit with Game Boy programming.
In the past I considered buying a Game Boy flashcart so that I could run demos and other scene ROMs on real hardware comfortably, but the price of such carts is a bit high.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Printing on the Game Boy Printer using an STM32F4</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_serial_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 16:33:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_serial_3/</guid>
      <description>In this third and final part of the project about the Game Boy serial communication I will explain how I managed to print on the Game Boy Printer from my PC using an STM32F4 as the bridge between the two. The encoding of the image into Game Boy tiles will happen on the PC, which will send it to the STM32F4 following the packet format of the Game Boy Printer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Game Boy Printer with an STM32F4</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_serial_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 16:33:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_serial_2/</guid>
      <description>In this second part of the project about interfacing the Game Boy serial communication with an embedded development board I will explain how I built a Virtual Game Boy Printer. The embedded board will be simulating a real Game Boy Printer, replying to the Game Boy following the protocol used by the Game Boy Printer so that the Game Boy sends the entire data meant to be print. This data will then be forwarded to my computer which will construct a PNG image out of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sniffing Game Boy serial traffic with an STM32F4</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_serial_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 02:33:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_serial_1/</guid>
      <description>In these series of blog posts I will write about the Game Boy serial communication protocol and how to interact with it by using an embedded development board. The code for the development board will be written in C, and the code running on the computer will be written in Rust.
The first part will consist on understanding the Game Boy serial communication protocol, becoming familiar with embedded development using the libopencm3 free/libre library and finally building a serial communication sniffer to capture the transmission of data on the Game Link Cable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enabling LUKS on the PocketCHIP</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/luks_on_chip/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2017 14:35:56 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/luks_on_chip/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I&amp;rsquo;ve recently acquired a handheld ARM computer with screen and keyboard called the PocketCHIP. The main board on the device is called the CHIP, which is a tiny ARM computer capable of running Linux that is sold for $9.
After flashing it with the CHIP 4.4 GUI OS, a flavor of Debian released by Next Thing Co (the company that made the PocketCHIP) I noticed I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to mount LUKS-encrypted partitions due to missing kernel modules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alpine Linux: Upgrading on Raspberry Pi</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/raspberry_pi_alpine_upgrade/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 23:18:39 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/raspberry_pi_alpine_upgrade/</guid>
      <description>This post describes the upgrade procedure I follow to upgrade my Raspberry Pi Alpine Linux installation. Alpine Linux on the Raspberry Pi runs from ramfs and thus the upgrading is not straightforward. Most of the details are taken from the Alpine Linux Wiki. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if Alpine Linux does any verification on the new downloaded release, so I&amp;rsquo;m doing that manually on another computer.
Upgrading First of all, replace the repository confiration to point to the new version:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rdiff-backup-1.2.8 in Alpine</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/rdiff-backup-alpine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 01:17:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/rdiff-backup-alpine/</guid>
      <description>Introduction A few days ago I wanted to start doing incremental backups from my laptop to my Raspberry Pi 2 running Alpine Linux. I&amp;rsquo;ve had used rdiff-backup for some years now and I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with it. rdiff-backup is similar to rsync, in the sense that lets you synchronize folders over the network, but it has two added nice features: when synchronizing, only the differences between the files that have changed are sent; and after every synchronization, the differences between the old version of the files and the new ones is kept.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry Pi: git server (cgit with lighttpd)</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/raspberry_pi_git/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 15:14:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/raspberry_pi_git/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post I will explain what&amp;rsquo;s required to set up a git server. We&amp;rsquo;ll use cgit to provide a web interface and also allow cloning/pulling through HTTP. ssh will also be available for cloning/pulling and pushing.
We&amp;rsquo;ll setup two groups of repositories: a public and a private one.
Cgit First of all, we&amp;rsquo;ll create a git user and move it&amp;rsquo;s home to the encrypted partition. For convenience we&amp;rsquo;ll also link that home directory to /git.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry Pi: setting up alpine, lighttpd and letsencrypt</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/raspberry_pi_alpine_lighttpd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 15:14:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/raspberry_pi_alpine_lighttpd/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post I will explain how to set up Alpine Linux for the RPi, with the necessary configuration for the RPi to power a USB hard drive, how to install lighttpd and configure automatic renewal of TLS certificates with lestencrypt.
Alpine Linux Alpine Linux can be installed on te RPi following the wiki guide.
After instalation, we add a new user which we will use for logging in:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry Pi 2 I/O benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/raspberry_pi_benchmarks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 15:03:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/raspberry_pi_benchmarks/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I&amp;rsquo;m currently setting up a Raspberry Pi 2 as a home server for various services. I&amp;rsquo;m gonna write a series of blog posts about how I configured my Raspberry Pi to achieve my goals, which will be mainly setting up a git server and a backup server.
Choice of distribution I discovered Alpine Linux while searching lightweight distributions for the Raspberry Pi. This is a lovely small Linux distribution: one of the first things I noticed is how fast it runs on the RPi due to using a ram filesystem by default; this is specially noticeable in the RPi because usualy the operating system resides in the micro-SD card, which usually offers really slow read and write operations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No more unencrypted emails to gpg contacts</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/check_mail_gpg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2016 00:13:28 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/check_mail_gpg/</guid>
      <description>I have been using mutt for about half a year already and I&amp;rsquo;m very happy with it. The previous email client I used was Thunderbird (with the Enigmail extension to handle GPG). There were two main reasons that made me switch.
The first one was that I often would like to check my email while I&amp;rsquo;m offline, and it seems that Thunderbird is not very good at this. Sometimes not all my email would have been downloaded (just the headers), and I also found it frustrating that after marking more than 50 emails as read while offline, they would be marked as unread again once I went back online.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible builds on Debian for GSoC 2015, 1st update</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/reproducible_builds_debian_gsoc2015_update_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 20:12:15 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/reproducible_builds_debian_gsoc2015_update_1/</guid>
      <description>This is the second blog post I&amp;rsquo;m writing about my experiences contributing to Debian for Google Summer of Code 2015 (check my first post)
Status update First month It&amp;rsquo;s been two months and a few days since the GSoC started. During the first month I worked on fixing specific packages, mainly concerning issues with timestamps, which is a very common source of unreproducibility. In many cases, during the build process files are compressed into gzip or zip archives, which store the creation time of files in the metadata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible builds on Debian for GSoC 2015</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/reproducible_builds_debian_gsoc2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 17:14:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/reproducible_builds_debian_gsoc2015/</guid>
      <description>This is the first blog post of a series I will be writing about my experiences contributing to Debian for Google Summer of Code 2015.
A bit about myself I&amp;rsquo;m a Spanish student doing a master&amp;rsquo;s in Computer Science in Barcelona. I graduated on Electrical Engineering (we call it Telecommunications here). I&amp;rsquo;ve always been interested in computing and programming and I have worked on several projects on my own using C, python and go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Full disk encryption on Samsung Chromebook with Arch Linux</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/full_disk_encryption_samsung_chromebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 23:58:40 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/full_disk_encryption_samsung_chromebook/</guid>
      <description>In this post I will explain the procedure I followed to have an Arch Linux install on a Samsung Chromebook 1 (XE303C12-A01US) with full disk encryption using kernel 3.8.
Kernel compilation and preparing SD card Install dependencies Install the necessary depdendencies (In my case I was running ubuntu). Mainly you need the tools for crosscompiling the kernel, configure u-boot and partition the SD card with a GPT partition table.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Booting the GameBoy with a custom logo</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_custom_logo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2014 01:35:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_custom_logo/</guid>
      <description>With the cartridge emulator implemented on an STM32F4 we can do some cool stuff. For example, we can make the GameBoy boot with our own custom logo!
Bootstrap ROM When the GameBoy boots, an intenral Bootstrap ROM is mapped to the beginning of the memory and execution begins. This bios is in charge of initializing the hardware as well as scrolling the Nintendo logo and checking that the cartridge i valid.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emulating a GameBoy Cartridge with an STM32F4. Part 2</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_cartridge_emu_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 19:46:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_cartridge_emu_2/</guid>
      <description>This post is a continuation of Emulating a GameBoy Cartridge with an STM32F4. Part 1
We have analyzed the memory bus of the GameBoy in order to obtain the timing information of the different signals involved in the read and write operations happening on the cartridge. We will now proceed to develop a system to emulate the behaviour of the cartridge with the STM32F4.
About voltage levels As we noticed in the previous post, the GameBoy works at 5V whereas the STM32F4 works at 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emulating a GameBoy Cartridge with an STM32F4. Part 1</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_cartridge_emu_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 03:33:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/gameboy_cartridge_emu_1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The following project consists on emulating the functionality of a GameBoy cartridge with the development board STM32F4. The system is fully functional and is able to emulate real cartridges (as well as homebrew games) of the type ROM Only and MBC1 (Memory Block Controller 1). In this post I will explain how I managed to achieve this.
Motivation Current flashcart systems commonly use a design consisting on a FPGA or CPLD controlling the logic of the emulated cartridge (memory banking, RAM access, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 17:04:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lizard.niobe.cc/blog/post/first/</guid>
      <description>I had been planning on creating a blog to write about the stuff I do on my free time for a while. In this blog I plan to write about the projects I develop as well as talking about interesting things I lean about technology, hardware, security, embedded systems, programming languages and more.
My first thought was to use a WordPress hosted at wordpress.com, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want the adds. I searched on the net for alternatives and found out about the static website generators, which allow you to host the content in a static web server such as your github personal page.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>