<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bsd on Dhole&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://dhole.github.io/categories/bsd/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bsd on Dhole&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 00:15:20 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://dhole.github.io/categories/bsd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Collapse Ready Operating Systems - FreeBSD</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os_freebsd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 00:15:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os_freebsd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post belongs to the Collapse Ready Operating System series.  See &lt;a href=&#34;https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os&#34;&gt;this&#xA;post&lt;/a&gt; for an introduction.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;prelude&#34;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My last post in this series was more than two years ago.  When I started the&#xA;series I had an initial plan to test the three most well known BSD operating&#xA;systems, and after publishing articles for NetBSD and OpenBSD I soon&#xA;started doing my homework with FreeBSD; unfortunately I had a lot of hiccups.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;ve made 4 different attempts at achieving the objectives in this series with&#xA;FreeBSD, the last one being last week, and none of them were fully successful.&#xA;The reason for trying several times instead of publishing the first result was&#xA;to see if some of the issues I encountered were temporary or bugs of a&#xA;particular release; but at the end I decided to publish the results I have.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collapse Ready Operating Systems - NetBSD</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os_netbsd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 12:00:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os_netbsd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a blog post in the Collapse Ready Operating System series.  Read &lt;a href=&#34;https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os&#34;&gt;this&#xA;post&lt;/a&gt; for an introduction.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;netbsd&#34;&gt;NetBSD&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This time I have chosen &lt;a href=&#34;https://netbsd.org&#34;&gt;NetBSD&lt;/a&gt;.  I have used NetBSD previously in my Raspberry Pi (the first version).  I had a lot of fun building packages for ARM from the raspberry pi and trying them out (and finding bugs as well).  I remember fondly the regular &lt;a href=&#34;https://mail-index.netbsd.org/port-arm/2022/10/26/msg007897.html&#34;&gt;status reports&lt;/a&gt; made by Jun Ebihara along with raspberry pi images with many packages already installed.  I also remember building a raspberry pi image myself from a Linux host on amd64 using cross-compilation: I was quite impressed with how easy the process was.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collapse Ready Operating Systems - OpenBSD</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os_openbsd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 00:15:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os_openbsd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a blog post in the Collapse Ready Operating System series.  Read &lt;a href=&#34;https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os&#34;&gt;this&#xA;post&lt;/a&gt; for an introduction.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;openbsd&#34;&gt;OpenBSD&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The OS analyzed in this post is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.openbsd.org/&#34;&gt;OpenBSD&lt;/a&gt;.  I&amp;rsquo;ve&#xA;tried OpenBSD a few times in the past: once as a personal web server on an old&#xA;PC, and then as a desktop in a laptop as a secondary system.  That was a few&#xA;years ago.  My memories from it are that the system was very clean, everything&#xA;worked as expected, the performance was significantly slower than linux and&#xA;that I really appreciated all the care the developers put on the security side.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collapse Ready Operating Systems - Intro</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 12:23:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nowadays we live in a hyperconnected World that relies heavily on Internet&#xA;connection for day to day tasks in all levels.  I&amp;rsquo;m not very happy with this&#xA;relience of assuming Internet access 24h for everything, as I think it&#xA;disempowers the user.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For example, whereas people before used to buy and own media, now they buy a&#xA;license to stream such media from the cloud.  This means that the user only has&#xA;access to the media as long as the platform exists, and we know that this is no&#xA;guarantee for the future.  It also means that the user can&amp;rsquo;t easily share the&#xA;media with their friends, that the consumption of the media can only be done in&#xA;authorized devices, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
