<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linux on Dhole&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://dhole.github.io/categories/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linux on Dhole&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 12:23:20 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://dhole.github.io/categories/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Collapse Ready Operating Systems - Intro</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 12:23:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/collapse_ready_os/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nowadays we live in a hyperconnected World that relies heavily on Internet&#xA;connection for day to day tasks in all levels.  I&amp;rsquo;m not very happy with this&#xA;relience of assuming Internet access 24h for everything, as I think it&#xA;disempowers the user.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For example, whereas people before used to buy and own media, now they buy a&#xA;license to stream such media from the cloud.  This means that the user only has&#xA;access to the media as long as the platform exists, and we know that this is no&#xA;guarantee for the future.  It also means that the user can&amp;rsquo;t easily share the&#xA;media with their friends, that the consumption of the media can only be done in&#xA;authorized devices, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NFS server over WireGuard in Alpine</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/nfs_wireguard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 13:27:31 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/nfs_wireguard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently built a new storage server at home consisting of 6x2TB hard&#xA;drives configured as RAID-Z2 with ZFS.  For the operating system I have chosen&#xA;Alpine Linux, which is a distribution that I really like for its&#xA;lightweightness and its simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Previously I had a storage server running Debian which I was sharing via sshfs.&#xA;sshfs is really easy to set up, as you just need to be running an ssh server,&#xA;nevertheless it has some disadvantages:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinkpad Helix 2 with Linux</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/thinkpad_helix2_linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 20:54:53 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/thinkpad_helix2_linux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;preface&#34;&gt;Preface&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve bought a second hand Thinkpad Helix 2nd Gen with the intention of&#xA;using it mainly as a tablet to read PDF documents and comics (although I may&#xA;use it for Internet browsing and occasional development).  I like running free&#xA;software on my computers and so I decided to use GNU/Linux with this&#xA;tablet/laptop.  Here I will explain all the issues I encountered and how I&#xA;solved them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pulseaudio for multi-user Linux</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/pulseaudio_multiple_users/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 20:54:53 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/pulseaudio_multiple_users/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-setup&#34;&gt;My setup&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For some time I&amp;rsquo;ve been using several unix users for my daily work in my&#xA;desktop computer.  After trying out Qubes OS for some time (an OS that achieves&#xA;security by compartmentalization: different kinds of activites are performed in&#xA;a different VM, isolating the data of each activity from each other), I came&#xA;back to GNU/Linux and realized that there&amp;rsquo;s already a security separation in&#xA;Unix (albeit not as secure as virtualization as in Qubes): users.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enabling LUKS on the PocketCHIP</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/luks_on_chip/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2017 14:35:56 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/luks_on_chip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently acquired a handheld ARM computer with screen and keyboard called&#xA;the &lt;a href=&#34;https://getchip.com/pages/pocketchip&#34;&gt;PocketCHIP&lt;/a&gt;.  The main board on the&#xA;device is called the &lt;a href=&#34;https://getchip.com/pages/chip&#34;&gt;CHIP&lt;/a&gt;, which is a tiny&#xA;ARM computer capable of running Linux that is sold for $9.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After flashing it with the &lt;em&gt;CHIP 4.4 GUI&lt;/em&gt; OS, a flavor of Debian released by&#xA;Next Thing Co (the company that made the PocketCHIP)  I noticed I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able&#xA;to mount LUKS-encrypted partitions due to missing kernel modules.  In this post&#xA;I will explain what I had to do to build and install the missing modules&#xA;without the need to replace the entire kernel.  If you want to install a new&#xA;and different kernel you will need to follow a more involved process because&#xA;the WiFi and GPU drivers aren&amp;rsquo;t in the kernel sources and require you to build&#xA;them apart (and also fiddle with the device tree).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alpine Linux: Upgrading on Raspberry Pi</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/raspberry_pi_alpine_upgrade/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 23:18:39 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/raspberry_pi_alpine_upgrade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post describes the upgrade procedure I follow to upgrade my Raspberry Pi&#xA;Alpine Linux installation.  Alpine Linux on the Raspberry Pi runs from ramfs&#xA;and thus the upgrading is not straightforward.  Most of the details are taken&#xA;from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.alpinelinux.org/wiki/Upgrading_Alpine#Upgrading_to_latest_release&#34;&gt;Alpine Linux&#xA;Wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if Alpine Linux does any verification on the new downloaded&#xA;release, so I&amp;rsquo;m doing that manually on another computer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;upgrading&#34;&gt;Upgrading&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First of all, replace the repository confiration to point to the new version:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>rdiff-backup-1.2.8 in Alpine</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/rdiff-backup-alpine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 01:17:17 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/rdiff-backup-alpine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I wanted to start doing incremental backups from my laptop to my&#xA;Raspberry Pi 2 running Alpine Linux.  I&amp;rsquo;ve had used rdiff-backup for some years&#xA;now and I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with it.  rdiff-backup is similar to rsync, in the&#xA;sense that lets you synchronize folders over the network, but it has two added&#xA;nice features: when synchronizing, only the differences between the files that&#xA;have changed are sent; and after every synchronization, the differences between&#xA;the old version of the files and the new ones is kept.  In other words, it keeps&#xA;backwards in time incremental backups, allowing you to revert the files in time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry Pi: git server (cgit with lighttpd)</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/raspberry_pi_git/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 15:14:27 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/raspberry_pi_git/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain what&amp;rsquo;s required to set up a git server.  We&amp;rsquo;ll use&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://git.zx2c4.com/cgit/&#34;&gt;cgit&lt;/a&gt; to provide a web interface and also allow&#xA;cloning/pulling through HTTP.  ssh will also be available for cloning/pulling&#xA;and pushing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll setup two groups of repositories: a public and a private one.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;cgit&#34;&gt;Cgit&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First of all, we&amp;rsquo;ll create a &lt;em&gt;git&lt;/em&gt; user and move it&amp;rsquo;s home to the encrypted&#xA;partition.  For convenience we&amp;rsquo;ll also link that home directory to &lt;code&gt;/git&lt;/code&gt;.  This&#xA;will be useful to have nice paths for our repositories.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry Pi: setting up alpine, lighttpd and letsencrypt</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/raspberry_pi_alpine_lighttpd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 15:14:27 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/raspberry_pi_alpine_lighttpd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain how to set up &lt;a href=&#34;https://alpinelinux.org/&#34;&gt;Alpine&#xA;Linux&lt;/a&gt; for the RPi, with the necessary configuration&#xA;for the RPi to power a USB hard drive, how to install lighttpd and configure&#xA;automatic renewal of TLS certificates with lestencrypt.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;alpine-linux&#34;&gt;Alpine Linux&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Alpine Linux can be installed on te RPi following the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.alpinelinux.org/wiki/Raspberry_Pi&#34;&gt;wiki&#xA;guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After instalation, we add a new user which we will use for logging in:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;adduser green&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After logging in with our new user (using password) we&amp;rsquo;ll add some ssh public&#xA;keys for future logins:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry Pi 2 I/O benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/raspberry_pi_benchmarks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 15:03:12 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/raspberry_pi_benchmarks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently setting up a Raspberry Pi 2 as a home server for various services.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m gonna write a series of blog posts about how I configured my Raspberry Pi to&#xA;achieve my goals, which will be mainly setting up a git server and a backup&#xA;server.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;choice-of-distribution&#34;&gt;Choice of distribution&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I discovered &lt;a href=&#34;https://alpinelinux.org/&#34;&gt;Alpine Linux&lt;/a&gt; while searching&#xA;lightweight distributions for the Raspberry Pi.  This is a lovely small Linux&#xA;distribution: one of the first things I noticed is how fast it runs on the RPi&#xA;due to using a ram filesystem by default; this is specially noticeable in the&#xA;RPi because usualy the operating system resides in the micro-SD card, which&#xA;usually offers really slow read and write operations.  Another really nice&#xA;feature is that it&amp;rsquo;s security-oriented, and as such the kernel is patched with&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.grsecurity.net/&#34;&gt;grsecurity/PaX&lt;/a&gt; and the userland binaries (I&#xA;understand that means all packages- too) are compiled with hardening features:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Position-independent_code&#34;&gt;Position Independent Executables&#xA;(PIE)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.osdev.org/Stack_Smashing_Protector&#34;&gt;stack&#xA;smashing protection&lt;/a&gt;.  This&#xA;distribution uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.musl-libc.org/&#34;&gt;musl libc&lt;/a&gt; instead of glib and&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://busybox.net/&#34;&gt;busybox&lt;/a&gt; to provide all the basic utilities, decisions&#xA;that help making it small and lightweight.  I should also mention that OpenRC is&#xA;used for the init system (instead of following the current trend of switching to&#xA;systemd).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No more unencrypted emails to gpg contacts</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/check_mail_gpg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2016 00:13:28 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/check_mail_gpg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been using mutt for about half a year already and I&amp;rsquo;m very happy with it.&#xA;The previous email client I used was Thunderbird (with the Enigmail extension to&#xA;handle GPG).  There were two main reasons that made me switch.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first one was that I often would like to check my email while I&amp;rsquo;m offline,&#xA;and it seems that Thunderbird is not very good at this.  Sometimes not all my&#xA;email would have been downloaded (just the headers), and I also found it&#xA;frustrating that after marking more than 50 emails as read while offline, they&#xA;would be marked as unread again once I went back online.  With mutt I&amp;rsquo;m using&#xA;mbsync (which apparently is faster than offlineimap) to sync my email to a local&#xA;folder with a cron job.  I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be happier.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible builds on Debian for GSoC 2015, 1st update</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/reproducible_builds_debian_gsoc2015_update_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 20:12:15 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/reproducible_builds_debian_gsoc2015_update_1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the second blog post I&amp;rsquo;m writing about my experiences contributing to Debian for Google Summer of Code 2015 (check my &lt;a href=&#34;https://dhole.github.io/post/reproducible_builds_debian_gsoc2015/&#34;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;status-update&#34;&gt;Status update&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-month&#34;&gt;First month&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been two months and a few days since the GSoC started. During the first month I worked on fixing specific packages, mainly concerning issues with timestamps, which is a very common source of unreproducibility. In many cases, during the build process files are compressed into gzip or zip archives, which store the creation time of files in the metadata. This can lead to unreproducible results when there is timezone variation between builds (easily fixed setting the timezone to UTC before the compression happens). In some cases the compressed files are generated during the build, and thus add build times in the metadata of compressed files (in this case the creation date of the files needs to be normalized somehow).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible builds on Debian for GSoC 2015</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/reproducible_builds_debian_gsoc2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 17:14:05 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/reproducible_builds_debian_gsoc2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first blog post of a series I will be writing about my experiences contributing to Debian for Google Summer of Code 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-bit-about-myself&#34;&gt;A bit about myself&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a Spanish student doing a master&amp;rsquo;s in Computer Science in Barcelona. I graduated on Electrical Engineering (we call it Telecommunications here). I&amp;rsquo;ve always been interested in computing and programming and I have worked on several projects on my own using C, python and go. My main interests in the field are programming languages, security, cryptography, distributed and decentralized systems and embedded systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full disk encryption on Samsung Chromebook with Arch Linux</title>
      <link>https://dhole.github.io/post/full_disk_encryption_samsung_chromebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 23:58:40 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dhole.github.io/post/full_disk_encryption_samsung_chromebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain the procedure I followed to have an Arch Linux&#xA;install on a Samsung Chromebook 1 (XE303C12-A01US) with full disk encryption&#xA;using kernel 3.8.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;kernel-compilation-and-preparing-sd-card&#34;&gt;Kernel compilation and preparing SD card&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;install-dependencies&#34;&gt;Install dependencies&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Install the necessary depdendencies (In my case I was running ubuntu). Mainly&#xA;you need the tools for crosscompiling the kernel, configure u-boot and partition&#xA;the SD card with a GPT partition table.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;sudo apt-get install u-boot-tools gcc-arm-linux-gnueabihf &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    binutils-arm-linux-gnueabihf cgpt device-tree-compiler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;set-up-some-directories-and-download-arch-and-kernel-sources&#34;&gt;Set up some directories and download arch and kernel sources&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;TMP_PATH&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;pwd&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;/chromeos&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mkdir -p $TMP_PATH&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;cd $TMP_PATH&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mkdir -p root&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mkdir -p mnt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Download my custom files&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
